- My name is Searls, my
non-Twitter name is Justin,
feel free to call me either.
This is what my face looked like in 2011
and thanks to how social
media branding works
I'm now stuck with it forever.
I work for a company called Test Double,
we're a software agency who's on a mission
to improve how the world writes software.
You can learn more
about us up at that URL.
The title of this presentation
is How to Program,
and it's a rumination on a word workflow,
two-part word, work
being what programs are,
their structure and behavior,
flow being how we program
our thoughts and actions.
And when I look back on
my experience learning
as a computer science student,
they taught me things like data structures
and P vs NP and Big O
analysis and cryptography,
and not very much about how
to think or how to work.
And bootschools nowadays
are actually analogous,
even though there are more
market practical skills
like web standards, and system tooling,
and languages and frameworks,
not so much how to think
through problems and solve
stuff, and really write code.
And you might think that's
the job of thoughtleaders,
'cause the word thought is
right there, but really,
thoughtleaders, when they're
talking about design patterns
or SOLID principles, even
when they talk about Agile
and Test-Driven Development,
those are nice 'cause they
describe work activities
but it's pretty discreet and mostly about
how people interact,
not so much how to think through things.
So it's reasonable to ask
when do we actually learn
flow as programmers, who
teaches us how to think?
And if you're lucky, 10
years into your career,
you'll stumble upon, or
somebody will show you
the only productivity tip
that any of us have ever been taught,
the Pomodoro technique,
(audience laughing and applauding)
where you work for 20 minutes
and then you take a three minute
break, it's really awesome,
but honestly it kinda
feels like you put 10 years
of hard service in to
get a $4 plastic pin,
it's kinda insulting that that's the best
that we have to offer.
So sure, somehow we all
learned what programs are,
but I'd hazard a guess that most of us,
nobody ever really
taught us how to program.
Look no further than a Google
search, how to program,
and you get a whole bunch
of terrible results,
starting with the traditional way
of teaching people how to program.
You start with nothing and
then somebody shows you
a completely finished
example, the finished product,
what the program should be,
and then as for connecting
it it's good luck, have fun.
And every single computer
science assignment
that I had in college really resembled
the How to Draw an Owl comic,
where you start with two circles and then
go draw the rest of the owl.
(audience laughing)
And I spent entire
weekends cooped up in a lab
trying to figure out,
staring at a blank editor,
and no idea how to write code.
And it was that moment that I realized
that programming's almost
a philosophical activity
that happens mostly in our heads.
Of course we've now innovated quite a lot
in programmer education
since I was in college,
now we, instead of just
one big finished example,
we've broken it up into two or three steps
over the course of a book or a screencast,
but very rarely does the
prose or the explanation
actually explain the thinking
of how to make that thing more real.
It might take years before
you're able to imitate
even an example application from a book.
But that word imitation stands out
because I think that most of us
are just imitating other programmers,
we see somebody successful or well-known,
and we just try to do things
like they seem to be doing things,
and that's how we learn and get by.
You can see that this is
endemic in our society
as programmers because we're
really bad at how questions.
If I ask how do I know when
to create a new method,
when should I break this thing up
into more than one thing?
You get really unsophisticated responses,
like, "Methods should be
about three lines long."
(audience laughing)
And when my wife, she
likes telling this story,
when she was in first grade, Becky,
she was told by a teacher that
sentences were two lines long
and so then dutifully,
for the next several years
until she was corrected,
she just stamped a period at
the end of every other line.
(audience laughing)
And that's funny 'cause
she's not an adult,
and yet here we are with these
unsophisticated ideas like,
"eh, methods should be
about three lines long,"
and no ability to communicate
above and beyond that.
But let's say in spite of all of this,
somehow you write a really
good program one day
and you're really proud
of it, and really happy.
And I ask you, okay, so
what actions were productive
or unproductive that
led you to that point?
Or what thoughts led you there,
which thought processes were
successful or unsuccessful,
would you be able to
answer those questions?
Most of us wouldn't be able to,
and it leads to rampant insecurity
from how we educate programmers,
to the work that we do,
to the colleagues that we
keep, and the overall industry.
Now 99% of the work that I have done
as a professional programmer
could be boiled down as
a business person trying
to get a spreadsheet
onto the internet.
(audience laughing)
And yet it's taken me 10 years or so
to even become a merely
competent programmer,
clearly something's wrong
in how we teach people to program.
And this industry is 60 or 70 years old,
but we're still searching
for silver bullets,
we always are externalizing the problem
and hoping the next
language, or framework,
or library, or process is gonna suddenly
make programming explicable,
and it never works out.
And think about that situation
where everyone's either
making stuff up as they go
or pretending they understand it,
who's gonna succeed in that environment?
It's genuinely brilliant people
and people with the
overconfidence of having been told
that they're brilliant their whole lives.
So imagine that you don't
look like other programmers
and you walk into a room,
and you lack that privilege
of having been told that
you're brilliant by society,
this is a terrifying
line of work to walk into
'cause no one can actually
explain how to program.
And I think that if you
wanna make programming
a more diverse and inclusive industry,
we really need to solve this.
(audience applauding)
And it's obvious that
the industry has no idea
how software works,
because they're constantly
analogizing it to literally
any other industry,
like construction, or
design, or manufacturing.
And because of that they
control the handful of things
that they do understand, like estimates,
and when people work, and where they work,
instead of the true nut of it
which is how we think
as software developers
and how we solve problems.
And so how do we fix it?
Well fortunately, yesterday at Keynote
DHH offered us one solution.
(audience laughing)
But I'm gonna talk about a different one,
I'm gonna talk about feedback loops,
because programmers, through compilation,
and through testing,
we're used to establishing feedback loops
to make forward progress,
and we can do the same things
inside of our heads
improving as developers.
We're gonna practice this today
by reflecting on the actions we take
and whether they're successful or not,
and how to improve our actions.
You can do the same thing for feelings
and actually reflect
on your emotional state
so that you can reinforce
positive emotions
or mitigate negative ones.
And, spoiler alert, you can
actually think about thinking,
(audience chuckling)
and produce better thought processes
that turn out to be more productive.
This is really the path to
programmer enlightenment,
but I realize that we're
starting from scratch here,
we gotta walk before we can run,
and ask yourselves what
do we do with teams
that are still emotionally immature
they struggle to even talk about feelings?
Well, we hand them
crappy personality tests
like the Myers-Briggs Type Indicator.
If you're not familiar
with the Myers-Briggs
just know that it's the worst type system.
(audience laughing)
The reason we rag on it
is 'cause it puts people
into these silly buckets
like ENTJ and ISFP,
and the implication is that there's only
16 types of people out there,
but we know that there's much, much more.
But when you're starting from zero,
16 starts sounding pretty good,
so that's why today I
am pleased to announce
the Searls-Briggs Type Indicator.
(audience laughing)
And instead of pontificating to you today
about how to program,
and dictating that this
is the magical way,
this is the silver bullet,
instead I'm just gonna
humbly take my own test,
show you how I feel and my inclinations
and my personality, and what I've done
over the course of my career
to reflect and improve, and
result in better outcomes
as a programmer.
To do that we need an example feature,
so let's make one up.
Like I mentioned, I work
at a company Test Double,
and we have always been
a distributed company,
but we're still learning
that that does not mean
evenly distributed.
So if you've got a flat organization
you might think that there's all these
spontaneous relationships that form,
but of course that's not accurate.
We all have our assigned pairs
and we all phone home
to an account manager.
Our org chart looks like one of those
1980's suction cup ball things,
but there's nothing
wrong with that per se,
unless, say two people on the team
both really wanna learn Elm.
But there's nothing systemically
that's gonna get those two people
talking together necessarily,
so somebody raised the idea,
why don't we have virtual
coffee dates on the team,
and just randomly assign
people to talk to each other
that otherwise wouldn't be.
There's actually an
expression from math though,
it's called The Handshake Problem,
which just calculates the number
of potential relationships
of any group of people,
and you see that there's
just tons of them.
And so what the system should do
is just send an email every week
to pair up people who might not otherwise
be talking to one another,
and tell 'em go spend 15 minutes
on this Google Hangout URL
and chat about something,
it doesn't have to be about work.
And so we're gonna put my test to the test
and build this feature together
this morning as a group.
And the first bucket
that I'm gonna put us in
is Sensitive versus Fearless,
and the first question is,
I prefer hearing all
requirements up front,
even if I can't tackle
them all right away.
I strongly disagree with that,
I get overwhelmed really easily.
Two, adding to a long function
feels like more code just won't fit.
Absolutely, once I hit a
certain amount of complexity
I can't imagine adding another case.
Three, I look forward to being assigned
to new projects and teams.
No way, new projects give me night sweats.
Four, I often feel paralyzed
while staring at a blank editor screen.
Yeah, I already admitted to that.
So does that make me
Sensitive or Fearless?
Pretty obvious in this
case, I'm Sensitive,
a big part of being Sensitive
is that I get overwhelmed easily.
So think about this feature
and all I've gotta do,
create pairs, great, that's not so hard,
but I do have to go and send the email,
and I also have to look
up all these people
from a database.
But I gotta be careful not to repeat
so I gotta randomize the pairings,
and I gotta not repeat
week to week either,
which means I also have to persist them.
So it's a lotta work, so I don't
wanna think about all that,
I just wanna focus on the core problem.
So my inclination is to just do that,
put a unit around it, think
hard about the problem,
I could do my little
Test-Driven Development thing,
and I'm feeling really good
about that unit of code,
so then I go to the controller
that's gonna call it,
and I realize that the method signature
doesn't quite line up.
Or somebody else might say,
hey, this unit you just made
is doing all this extra redundant work
that's actually handled elsewhere.
My inclination was to overcome
that paralysis that I felt
and find some productivity
by just putting on blinders.
And I fell into that
rabbit hole often enough
that I had to think and reflect,
and actually have inverted
how I work as a programmer.
So what I just showed you is often called
bottom-up programming, but
now I practice top-down,
it works better for me.
You might also call it outside-in,
where I think from the
perspective of the controller,
at the top level entry
point, and I start there,
and I ask what do I need?
Well I need something
to create these pairs,
and when your brain is focused that way,
the caller knows exactly
what inputs are available,
what output it's gonna want,
and it's also a way to minimize waste,
because it has the broader
context in terms of
what guard clauses need to be inserted
or can be omitted.
The other aspect of being Sensitive
is that I'm really afraid of failure,
and when you work outside-in,
you do have to juggle all these
different concerns at once
which can, again, be overwhelming.
And so what I try to do is
just rush into solving it,
my inclination is just
to open up an editor
and prove that I can write this code,
so I start with a module,
and I make a method,
I go load up a bunch of
users, I loop over them,
I skip anyone who's already
had their hand shaken,
otherwise I'll go an add a tuple
to represent a pairing, and then I'll go
and slam it through some mailer,
and now I feel really good,
'cause I just proved I could do it.
And someone will remind me,
remember you gotta randomize it,
and you don't wanna leave out
the 15th person every week,
and you've also gotta prevent
repeats from happening
week to week, and now
I'm terrified because
this is already really dense,
I don't know how I'm gonna
make it more complicated.
And I'm very familiar with
this corner of the room
as a result.
So I keep painting myself into this corner
and the root cause is fear,
I'm afraid of failing,
I'm afraid of big things
that I don't know how to break down.
So my solution is avoid that fear
by breaking things down
in a systematized way,
give myself some help.
And I've been practicing
over the last few years,
iterating on an approach
to Test-Driven Development
that I call Discovery Testing,
and it's really an effort in
breaking big, scary problems
into smaller, more manageable ones.
It works with, I start with just a test
of that top level thing.
So I write a single test
case, I invoke the thing,
and then I ask myself a crucial question,
what's the code that I wish I had,
that I could defer and
hand this work out to?
Well something to find these hands,
something to determine
who shakes whose hand,
something to mail them
and then persist them.
Then I use my test double library,
which in Ruby is "gimme",
so it creates these four fake things,
and I set up a stubbing,
so I say, hey, when finds_hands is called
it gets you this thing
to symbolize the hands,
and if I pass that to thing
that determines the shakes,
another stubbing'll give
me these handshakes.
This is all the test set-up I need
to be able to actually assert
that I mail out all those handshakes
and that I persist them.
Now this is an unusual-looking test
to a lot of you I'm sure,
but what it does is it perfectly specifies
the behavior of that top level unit.
And so I get this test to pass,
and I never have to worry
about that top level again.
In fact, if you list out
all the files that shake out
from just getting that test to pass,
now I have a pretty clear
work cut out for me,
I know exactly what I need to do,
I can start making forward progress.
So I start off with a big, scary thing,
but as I build that test
I identity the units
that I would need to
actually carve out the work,
and instead of one big scary thing,
I now have four more digestible problems
that I can focus on, and
if any of them are scary,
I now have in my back
pocket a tool that I can use
to reduce and break
things up even further.
The second bucket I'm gonna talk about
is Inventive versus Aesthetic,
so there's some quiz questions
to determine my type.
Question one, it's more important
to build the right thing
than to build the thing right.
Eh, these are both important,
but I'm more implementation-focused.
Question two, I love
experimenting with new tools,
frameworks, and build systems.
Not at all, I do spend a lot of my time
in open source here, but it's expressly
so I don't have to worry about it at work.
Question three, I strive to
write visually appealing code,
down to syntax and symmetry.
Absolutely, I don't know why,
but I really like
pretty, symmetrical code.
Question four, it's boring
when all the code in a project
is structured similarly.
I disagree, I really
like consistency in code.
So does that make me
Inventive or Aesthetic?
Well I think it makes
me a little Aesthetic.
And one part of being Aesthetic
is I have refined taste.
Now the problem with taste is
that nobody knows what it is
(audience laughing)
until somebody on your
team says, you know what,
I'd prefer a 300-line function
to all these well-named little small units
that you keep creating.
And then my face looks like this.
(audience laughing)
That's taste.
And so why do programmers
develop taste, well it's obvious,
when you're staring at
a blank editor screen,
there are infinitely many ways
to solve any given problem,
we need something to constrain ourselves,
some patterns to follow
to just not be stuck
in analysis paralysis forever.
And that's why I think that
prose is a much better analogy
to writing software than construction is.
In fact, I think of programming
as just communication
to the next developer
who's gonna pick it up,
and it's just hard
because it has to happen
through this filter
that's just formal enough
for an interpreter or a
compiler to understand.
And so when I hear this
feedback I reflect,
and I take it to mean as a critique,
that maybe I'm writing code
that's meant to be read
by myself as opposed to another human,
because the other developer,
they're not in the room,
so I tend to write code that I
think that I would wanna read
and this leads to self-centered design.
So if I just write a
book on design patterns
I'm gonna create a bunch
of units like services,
and factories, and repositories,
and I'm gonna feel really
brilliant having done all this,
but then somebody else could list out
all of the files I just
created in one big listing.
From their perspective, it's
gonna be inpenetrably complex,
it's a forest of all these objects,
no idea how things are gonna work.
And so now when I hear that critique,
they've got a pretty good point.
And I found this happen
on team after team,
and what it made me realize is
I gotta start working differently
to make my code more
discoverable and approachable
for other developers, and now
I do things much differently.
It started with realizing
programs are directed graphs,
so all of these units are really
kind of nodes in this graph
and all of the edges or
vertices are function calls.
So the Locator calls the Service,
which calls this Repository,
which calls this Mapper,
which instantiates Hands,
Service also calls this Factory,
which calls that thing and that thing.
And we already, 'cause we
think of programs this way,
we have some taste, we have
some constraining principles
that we share.
Like for instance, if this Repository
were to call this Service, we would all,
wait a second, that's a dependency cycle,
we realize there's a risk
of an infinite recursion
or stack overflow there.
And so most of the programs
that we write as developers
try to by acyclic diagraphs.
And remember my purpose
here is just to prove
that I'm right, I wanna
tell this person, no,
small units is better than
300 lines objectively,
and to do that I thought maybe
there's a liberating constraint,
maybe if I refine my taste
further I can solve this problem.
And where I landed was, I want
to express all of my features
not as just general graphs, but as trees,
because a tree is just a
special subtype of a graph,
you can take this exact
same menagerie of units
and organize it in a tree shape
where you have your
value objects on the left
and the feature behavior on the right.
And now if it's true that I
have any needless indirection,
it stands out in a tree 'cause
it's just got one child,
so that service locator, yeah,
I can probably get rid of that.
And if somebody asks, if
what they're looking for
is how to compare two hands,
they can search the tree
much more easily and quickly
than just a gigantic directory of files
and find what they're looking for,
so it's more discoverable.
The other aspect of my
Aesthetic is I'm a minimalist,
so when you look at our
app you see it's car,
it drives, you think
about what its function is
and why it exists.
When I look at our app,
all I see is the clutter and the mess.
(audience chuckling)
And as a minimalist,
my productivity goes up
when things are tidy and
symmetrical and terse,
and it goes down when things
are cluttered or inconsistent.
And what the software's
supposed to be doing
is its essential complexity,
everything it actually does
is its incidental complexity,
the other stuff,
think of everything that
goes into writing a program.
You're writing deploy
tooling and app config,
and dependencies, and
framework appeasement.
Then of course there's whatever
the app was supposed to do,
there's style rules,
continuous integration,
build systems, and then of
course unnecessary stuff.
As a minimalist, I'm the
person on the project
who's always chiseling away
to try to minimize the amount
of incidental complexity in the system,
and trying to maximize the
time that the team spends
on whatever's really important.
That means I'm always
tweaking my code style,
like maybe I'd start
writing a feature behavior
inside of my model objects,
but then separate them
out into separate units,
but then maybe make them cullables,
but maybe ultimately
land at module methods.
These are all fine, you can
debate the finer points,
but at the end of the day
they're really six of one,
half a dozen of the
other kinds of arguments.
And they represent a sort of trap,
because earlier I said
style rules, debating style,
is a type of incidental complexity
'cause style is subjective,
and so it changes around arbitrarily.
And arbitrary decisions
breed inconsistency,
and, oh it turns out that inconsistency
is another form of incidental complexity.
And so, oops.
Because if on Monday I
organize code this way,
and on Tuesday this way,
and Wednesday that way,
and then by Thursday I've
decided this is the best way
to organize code, everyone's
gonna get mad at me,
because I've just littered
36 custom little styles
all throughout the system.
So my temptation to
continuously be improving stuff
actually breeds inconsistency
and creates bigger messes
elsewhere, so I reflected on how,
I think what was happening is I'd chase
the local optimization at the expense
of the global optimization
of what's best for the overall project.
And I had to learn to
avoid this oscillation
in my design, and it really
required me to just realize
I'd spend the entire
project spinning my tires.
And so instead I decided
I need to just lock in these decisions,
and say we're just gonna
do things this style,
whether or not it's better
or worse, it doesn't matter,
so we can try to carve
out time to be productive.
And as I got better at that,
at flexing that muscle,
I could recognize where I'm
spinning my wheels earlier
and spend more of my
time being productive,
it was a way for me to
both be a minimalist
but also really consistent
in my applications,
even when it meant hewing really strongly
to arbitrary decisions of things
that didn't really matter.
And when you do that,
especially with your
incidental complexity,
it brings the essential
complexity into sharper relief,
so you can all as a
team really just focus,
spend more time on what
your app really needs to do.
The third bucket is Naive versus Leery.
Question one, publishing
metrics like code coverage
is always a good idea.
Eh, I think radical
transparency often backfires.
Question two, writing
good commit messages today
will pay off in the future.
Secret, I don't actually
read commit messages, so eh.
Three, software teams will
make smarter use of time
under pressure, disagree, I
think pressure kills cognition.
Four, software is generally
improving over time
and we are not doomed.
(audience laughing)
Pass, so does that make me Naive or Leery,
I'm starting to realize this
is a pretty obvious test,
in my case I'm Leery.
It all starts with my
distrust of all of you.
(audience laughing)
Because most teams operate
in a pressure cooker.
They're under pressure
to get as much stuff done
as fast as possible, and as a
result their brains turn off,
and it results in really,
really bad outcomes.
In fact it's not very
fair to pressure cookers
because pressure cookers
serve a useful purpose.
(audience chuckling)
So I'll find another analogy.
(audience laughing)
Where we're just being
squeezed for all of the Ruby
and JavaScript that we're worth,
and again, not being creative,
not resulting in good code.
One person on teams I don't trust
is I don't trust product owners,
I love 'em, but I don't trust 'em.
Back in the Waterfall
days, a product owner
would be able to specify 300 bullet points
of everything that they ever wanted
and then foist them upon us, and we'd say,
hey, this is awful, but in a
way at least it was honest,
they got to articulate everything
that they wanted up front,
it was just us who
didn't know how to handle
that much complexity.
Scrum and Agile stuff gave
us a little bit of a backbone
and we said, no sir, you only
get one index card at a time,
and in fact that's gonna be 20 points,
and I made up what points mean.
(audience laughing)
So naturally, then it becomes a debate of,
no, I think it's five points,
and any system can be gamed,
and really savvy product owners I know
are really good at this.
Like oh, you know, this
is not that complex,
it's just a little cartoon whale,
you guys can do that right, you have time.
And we'll say, oh yeah
sure, we can do that,
and then we realize it's much more complex
than we really thought, and
by then they're out to lunch
and we're left holding the bag.
So I don't trust product owners.
Of course someone I trust
even less than product owners
is other developers, and it's because
on day one of a feature
we neglect to realize
a very basic fact; our
brains can only hold
so much stuff in them at once.
And so I think the
developers have this biased
towards size and features to
just whatever number of things
they can hold in their head at a time,
and naturally, the conclusion that we draw
about how big our objects
and methods should be,
is the same size, 'cause then that way
we can just put all of
the things in one place,
it seems like the simple solution.
But then a month passes and somebody says,
hey, you need to add a
couple additional aspects
to this feature, it has to
do this and this as well.
Well, that means that the other stuff,
our brain is finite, we can't
keep it all in our heads
at once anymore, but units,
we can make files as long
as we want, and so we just,
even though we're incurring a paging cost,
we can slam in those additional
attributes to the feature.
But it creates a blindspot for us where
now that we're not thinking
about the persistence,
bugs can creep in through that door.
And if you work this way, a year passes,
and pretty soon your
units are just gigantic,
and they look like this and
they're riddled with bugs.
And normally day 400 is the
day and I get a phone call
saying, hey, can you
help improve our tests?
Of course this isn't a
testing problem right,
it's a complexity management problem,
and it's hard for me when
I see this cycle repeat
over and over again, to let that distrust
grow into cynicism, and that's not good.
And in fact, if I'm empathetic I realize
that at the root of this industry,
all of us really struggle to predict
how complexity is gonna change,
and to guess the complexity of stuff,
and I do it too.
And so what I wanna do
is change the question,
and instead focus on how to
prepare myself and other people
for the inevitable increase of complexity,
'cause on any maintained
system, almost any of them,
complexity's gonna go up over time,
it's just a matter of what
that graph looks like.
And so like Pascal, I made
up Searls' Wager in my head,
where sure, complexity
might remain constant,
or it might go up.
And yeah, we could keep writing
these brain-sized units,
or much smaller ones.
And if complexity doesn't
change, no harm no foul,
it doesn't really matter
how we factor our code,
but if it goes up, we
have a lot of evidence
that these larger units cause problems.
And the nice thing
about small ones is that
they can actually accommodate
some additional complexity
without too much pain.
And that's why on day one of every feature
I break things up into
itty bitty tiny units,
to the point where people criticize me.
And if you think that my units
are too small, don't worry,
because I trust that you're gonna go
and make 'em bigger later.
(audience laughing)
It'll work out.
It's a great way, if you
struggle with trying to make,
follow the Single Responsibility Principle
and have every object do one thing,
this makes it really, really easy,
in fact, this is what
the tree of functionality
shook out as in this example,
and every single unit
serves exactly one purpose,
and they all follow one of three rules
that I've observed over the
years of practicing this.
The parent nodes are delegator objects,
they don't really have
any logic or branching,
maybe just one if condition or something,
they mostly just break up the work
and hand it off to other things.
And the way that I happen to do that
is I use this Test-Driven Design
where I use test doubles
to identify and think up
what's the code I wish I had
that would actually do the real work?
What you wanna try to
maximize is these leaf nodes,
so this is where the core
logic of the application is,
it takes inputs and transforms
into some kinda output,
these are pure functions so
you don't need test doubles,
you just are actually testing real logic,
these are the kinds of unit tests
that everyone likes to write.
And it's sorta like functional programming
for people who wanna think too hard
about functional programming.
It makes it very accessible
because you can still do it in Ruby,
you don't have to change
languages or something.
On the left are my
values, and value objects,
they just wrap a little bit of data,
maybe they just hold
onto a hash or an array,
and the methods on them are only allowed
to elucidate the data and
answer questions about the data,
as opposed to doing feature work,
they're not there to
actually build features.
Instead I think of them as the sludge
that flows though the
pipes of my feature code,
they're the types in
those method signatures.
And even if all this abstraction
doesn't ultimately pay off,
and even if that feature doesn't
change a lot in the future,
the very worst case, I've got
a very discoverable system
of carefully named
things that are obvious,
and small and comprehensible,
so it's not the worst
outcome in the world.
The third aspect here is
that I distrust myself,
even more than all of you.
It's because I worry about the future,
and even though I'm not super confident
in Today Me's skills,
I'm even more worried
that my future self won't
be able to program either
for some reason.
And so when I'm writing a feature,
somebody says, build this thing,
I'll think about how to build it,
and then I'll build a message
in a bottle for myself
in the form of better
tests and documentation
and commit messages,
things to try to help.
And my future self,
who's wearing sunglasses,
is told to change that feature,
he gets really frustrated,
because what those tests mean is
now he's got a bunch of other stuff to do
every time he wants to make a change,
and my future self would
much rather just start fresh
and be able to write new code.
And so I kept trying to do myself favors
by writing a lot of extra tests,
and adding in all this
quality at the beginning,
but it would actually tie my hands,
and so I had to reflect
how do I bake quality
into my applications without
creating an undue burden
for my future self,
and so I started working
a little bit differently.
Because if this is our
tree of functionality
and our manager comes in
and says, new requirement,
thanks to some HR fiasco all
handshakes have to happen
between three people...
(audience chuckling)
the traditional way to solve this
is to carefully read the existing code,
add, remove, change
tests, change the code,
and then try to make as
small of a mess as possible,
and I say small mess
because any time the purpose
of a piece of code has been two things,
whenever we change a unit,
it carries with it technical debt,
it confuses the story of why it existed
because it's changed over time.
So instead I've been trying
to make my code disposable,
and what that means is that
when I look at this tree,
I search for all of the
affected units by the change,
these are two units that are gonna change,
and so then I find the smallest sub-tree
that encapsulates that change,
and so there it is right there.
And then I do something
unusual, I blow it all up,
I just knock it out, 'cause
I trust that my future self
is gonna be able to see
that top level thing
and understand what the contract is.
So there he is, he's gonna
drive out a new solution.
And as opposed to just
changing these old units
that implemented the logic the old way
and thus wrack up technical debt,
instead I trust him to
drive out a new solution.
And in fact, future us is
gonna have more experience
than present-day us,
they'll probably have
a better understanding
of the business, they'll be
able to write better units
in the future than we
ever could hope to today,
so this is a healthy way to work.
It does mean that I try
not to reuse code too much
in my feature code because any code reuse,
like if you have a method
that's called in nine places,
it's really hard to change that method,
'cause you have to consider
nine different placed callers
and what they need.
It's also really hard to
throw it away and replace it,
so I try not to reuse too much code.
And it also forced me
to let go of this idea
that maintainable code
has to live forever.
In fact, as opposed to
that, this incremental,
rewriting the small as
part of your process,
is a way to pay technical debt
without saving a rainy day fund
for when you finally get to refactor.
And in doing that, I
actually made myself happier,
'cause future me does
not want his job to be
fixing all of Justin's old janky tests
every time that he changes something.
It wants to be able to
write code for a living,
and so this process by
making death a part of life
while we're working through features,
is a great way to keep your
teams happy I've found.
The last bucket here is
Economical versus Thorough.
The question one, better
to ship code quickly
than wait until everything is tested.
Eh, I feel like I'd just be
bailing out water in that case.
Two, design principles are useful,
but most teams waste
too much time on them.
It's possible for sure, but
few teams are at risk of this.
Three, most teams lack a
sufficient understanding
of their dependencies.
Absolutely, 90% of us have no clue
how most of our code
works in our applications.
And four, it's okay for everyone on a team
to maintain separate coding styles.
I actually strongly disagree,
'cause this leads to siloed development,
it's kinda like a Conway's Law of style.
So does that make me
Economical or Thorough?
Well of course it makes me Thorough.
Some of you are noticing
that this spells salt,
(audience laughing)
that's because when you make up the quiz
you can make it spell whatever you want.
(audience laughing)
It's gonna surprise a few
of you to learn today,
I have a confession to make,
I'm a bit of a control freak,
and that means I'm dubious of free stuff.
So when you see a sign
that says free puppies,
all I read is extra
work, and another thing
in our industry that
makes me think extra work
is open source.
And so just keep that in your head
next time you're on GitHub
asking for free labor
from an open source maintainer,
imagine you're yelling at a puppy instead,
because who yells at puppies, you jerk.
(audience laughing)
And open source isn't free
because just like puppies
we have to learn how to use it,
we have to learn how it's
changing and follow it,
and it's not just this panacea
that we can pull off the internet
instead of having to
build stuff ourselves.
And if that open source has a bug,
in theory sure, we can fix it ourselves,
but in practice we're not gonna
understand all that stuff,
we're probably gonna have
to rely on a maintainer
or an expert to come and fix it later.
And finally, if we have a,
let's say this is our graph of objects,
and it's all very consistent everywhere,
and we slam in some third party API,
that's gonna create a certain
amount of friction and pain
because it's going to look
like all of our other objects.
In fact, third part dependencies
have this really nasty
habit of leaking references
all over our code base, which
makes it really hard to change
or replace or upgrade those
third part dependencies
over time.
So my temptation of all
these negative things
about open source and puppies, is to,
well I don't have a puppy first of all,
again, much to my wife
Becky's consternation,
but two, I try to avoid using open source.
That's what my gut tells me to do,
but that's increasingly
untenable these days
'cause I'd be reinventing
wheels constantly.
So I had to change how I thought
about open source instead
to maybe protecting myself
from its blast radius,
as opposed to avoiding it entirely.
And the way that I do
that is I write wrappers
of all of the third
party code that I write.
In fact we already have
one up on this tree,
it's that Finds Hands unit on the left.
So this is a wrapper object,
and it starts as just
a well-named delegator,
it's a no-op, it doesn't
do anything interesting.
But it comes to encode
all of our understanding
of that dependency, it is the
carpet under which we sweep
all of the stuff that we have to do
to make that third party dependency happy.
And I integration test it
but only in proportion
to how suspicious I am
of it breaking, otherwise I trust
that it itself is tested well.
And it might feel like
needless indirection,
but I need you to trust me that it's not.
Of course, if this is where
we're calling Finds Hands
in our top level code,
and I just told you not
to trust other developers,
so you don't trust me,
you assume that that wrapper
is unnecessary let's say,
and instead of using that call
we're just gonna call it User.all instead.
That way it's much more direct,
we got rid of that needless indirection,
which means we have to update our test.
So this is our original test,
we can get rid of that fake finder
and instead have an array of real users
that we create in the database.
Of course, validation failed,
so now I have to add a birthdate,
some incidental other arbitrary thing
to make this work.
But I can also get rid
of this stubbing here
and pass real users
into the other stubbing,
and I gotta make an integration test
as opposed to a unit test.
And ask yourself now, what did we just do,
'cause the value of this test
used to be crystal clear,
its purpose was to break the work up
into four clear responsibilities,
and now what is it?
It's calling through to the database
so it's making sure that the thing works,
but only when three quarters
of the code pads are fake?
That doesn't seem right,
that seems wrong to me,
and it really becomes obviously wrong
when this becomes more complex,
'cause if we add a couple scopes
like only search for full
time and active employees,
then our test isn't enough anymore,
'cause those scopes are like branches,
so now we need two or three
test cases to cover everything.
And now it's abundantly obvious
that we sliced things wrong.
So when I hear teams complain
you have too many abstractions
or too many objects,
typically I think that's,
it's not wrong, it's
not that you're making
too many abstractions
so that no abstraction
is somehow better,
it's that you're probably mixing
the levels of abstraction in your system,
because life with wrappers is much easier.
If I look at that same thing
and dive into what that
wrapper looks like,
yes, on day one, in looks
like needless indirection,
but on day two when it gets more complex,
it's easy to write a test for this,
there's a place for that complexity to go.
And over time it might become
a little bit more complicated
as you distance yourself further here
with a transformer to a type that you own,
as opposed to an ActiveRecord user.
So let's say our boss comes in and says
we're gonna change from
ActiveRecord to the Sequel gem.
Traditionally this would really panic
everyone in the room
because you're gonna have
a billion references to ActiveRecord
all over your system,
but when you're writing wrappers carefully
of your third party dependencies,
you're actually preparing for yourself
an adapter interface that's minimal
and specifies exactly how
you use that dependency.
So you can even answer questions like
would it be possible to switch
to this third party thing?
And if you did, you could create
an alternate implementation
and run both in parallel for awhile.
It's a much, much better way to work,
and what I found is
it's a way to maintain,
still have all that
convenience of open source
and sucking in these useful libraries
while maintaining control
over how you work.
So when you're as introspective
about this stuff as I am
you run the risk of
explaining the universe
through yourself.
In fact if you ask
anyone who's ever worked
on a project with me what my
favorite way to write code is,
it's my way, and I'll fight you for it.
So my inclination is to
just work really hard
to convince you all that my way is best,
and I'd love to say that
that's an altruistic thing
and I want you all to
be better programmers,
but it's not, it's selfish.
What it really is is I'm afraid
I'm gonna have a manager someday
tell me that I can't write
code my favorite way anymore.
And when I reflect on that,
even if I were to come up with
a perfect way to write code
and hand it to you, I run
the risk of robbing you
of that same autonomy, and so
that wouldn't be good either,
and so that's why I'm getting out
of the silver bullet business.
So even though I talked a lot today
about how I program, I'm not
here to sell you on that,
I mean I hope you find some of it useful,
but what I really am here to sell you on
is the idea of pausing an introspecting
about how you act, feel, and
think while you're programming
so that it becomes more explicable to you,
and then you could articulate
it to other people,
and improve, and share.
And you might ask yourself, hey,
if we all start thoughtleading ourselves,
won't that just create chaos on our teams?
And I think that's
actually a valid concern,
so let's spend a minute
to talk about that.
Because earlier I said if you lock down
all those arbitrary decisions up front
you can spend more time being productive,
that's true individually,
but it's also true as teams,
and that's why when you have disagreements
with other people on a team,
you should aggressively pull this forward,
because the earlier you
have that discussion
and say okay, we'll use these semicolons,
or we'll follow this style,
if you can agree to that
stuff early and lock it in,
you'll as a team be more productive,
and in fact if you look
at the average team,
remember what I said earlier,
we're all just imitating
other programmers,
so most teams actually like
the idea of normalizing.
In fact, some of them like it too much,
where if you have a creative idea
of doing things differently,
oh, I don't wanna rock the boat,
I don't wanna do my own thing off here,
or go off the reservation, quote unquote,
so instead we tend to just gravitate
towards the lowest common
denominator on a lotta teams,
and that's not good.
But that's not you anymore right,
'cause after today
you're gonna be thinking
about how the actions you
take could be improved,
your feelings, improving
your thought processes,
and on your next team when you join a team
of all enlightened Hugh Jackmans,
(audience chuckling)
some of whom will be SALT,
and some of whom will be FINE,
which is literally what the
other four traits spell.
(audience laughing)
And some will be SALE
and some will be FALT,
when you look at this team, yeah sure,
they all have very strongly held opinions
of different ways of doing things,
but the one thing they have in common
is when they're approached
with a new idea,
they have a system for testing it
and figuring out whether
to adopt or reject it,
and so they're not afraid
of trying new things.
And that's why I think that
really introspected developers,
when they're on a team,
they might just look like
they're talking at the whiteboard all day,
but they can actually have
a multiplicative impact
on each other as they grow.
And that's really my dream today,
is that if we can, as an
industry, normalize the concept
of metacognition, and self-improvement,
so that we can explain how to program
this whole place might start
making a whole lot more sense.
And that is how to program.
(audience chuckling)
So I appreciate your time here today,
if you're looking for
a company to work with
that's gonna support you
on this kind of journey,
I hope you'd consider checking us out,
that's our page explaining what it's like
to work with us at Test Double,
and if you're a company that is looking
for additional developers on your team,
I hope you'd consider working with us.
We join other teams just
as additional developers
with an interest in helping
everyone get better as we go,
and you can learn more
about us on our site.
By the way, I really made
this quiz, it's a real thing,
I actually printed out 100
copies and I have it in my bag
so you can get a special
commemorative edition today,
if you come up and say hi
to me I'll hand you one,
I also have a lotta Test Double stickers.
If you don't wanna say hi to me in person
you an actually go to testdouble.com/salt
and fill it out, we made a Google Form,
and then two of our
agents yesterday actually
figured out how to automate Google Form
so it'll calculate your programmer type
and email you right away,
so I hope you go check that out too.
But most importantly of all,
I'm really thankful for this opportunity
and for your time this morning.
Thank you.
(audience applauding)