This talk is titled how to
scratch an itch in 200 repos
or less. @searls is my real name
My parents were quite prescient
and on-brand back when
they named me. This is
what my face looked
like in 2011 and
thanks to personal
branding, I'm now stuck with this
face forever because you might see it
from Twitter or Github
as my avatar
Just like Todd mentioned, I
co-founded an agency with him
Just like Todd mentioned, I co-founded an
agency with him 5 years ago called
Test Double. Our mission
in life is to improve
a lot of the stuff about software that sucks,
and one of the things that sucks a lot
is that most engineering teams
operate at capacity
and they don't have enough
slack in the system to improve
things like testing, and quality,
and craft. So we come in
to pair with those teams to
add enough capacity so that
we can all work together to make
stuff better. It might sound
familiar as a business model, it's
kind of like consulting except good
So if your team could
benefit from that sort of
thing, I hope you'll chat with me
or Todd tonight or tomorrow
So, yeah, how to scratch an itch
You might be able to
infer from that title that this
is a talk about creativity
Everyone loves creativity, "yay!
creativity!" That's a good
thing, right, ok, cool, let's talk
about creativity. …So what is
creativity, exactly? It's one
of those axiomatic
concepts that we generally
don't interrogate
or introspect much on, and
I forced myself to
think about this when I was
designing this talk and
The first thing that came to mind
is that creativity is a lot like passion
Passion's hot right now. We got all
these passion projects. Look at all
these passionate logos for passion
projects that people have
made. But personally I don't
get on board with a movement
until I can find a way to engage
with a brand
and its hashtag. So the American
Express passion project.
And it actually serves as a
really good example of why
passion doesn't equal creativity,
because it fizzles out
kind of like domain
name registrations
So the Amex passion
project is just gone
now. So, no, passion
isn't quite
what creativity is. You might
say "is creativity art?"
You certainly—coding feels
creative, right?
We know it's a creative
enterprise, but not all of our
code is art, when I put
it up on a screen
You know, it's mostly functional
most of the time. It certainly can
be art, but it doesn't seem like
the best metaphor
or abstraction. You could say,
is creativity vision
and foresight? If we had a
crystal ball where you could see
where the cloud is and where it's
going to go and there might be an
aspect of that, but that's not
in itself building anything
it's just prognostication,
so vision's not enough
And I thought about
this at length to try to
figure out, "am I creative?
are you creative?"
And if I was forced to think
in those terms
and that popular framing about
creativity like filling out a survey
Are you incredibly passionate? Do you
create beautiful things?
Can you see into the future? Of
course most of us would say no
to all three of those things, so
certainly we're not
creative. That's a really high
bar to clear. Creative people
are these magical unicorns and
that's not me, that's not us.
That's kind of disappointing.
We can
usually at least relate to the idea
of a creative spark, right, like we
have an idea in the back of our heads
we're walking down the street and an
idea occurs and then of course
what happens next is we just
effortlessly create amazing things
based on that idea
Unfortunately, that doesn't comport
with my experience. Actually
I have a—creative ideas,
they stress me
out. That spark, tells me—
I'm already really busy
how am I going to find the
time or the capability to go
and accomplish that thing
these ideas they sort of scare me,
because I don't think I'm—gonna
have fear, uncertainty, and doubt I'm not going
to be able to do them. Where does that spark
come from? Is there some big
dragon breathing fire
behind me? Should I be running
from my ideas or I'm going to burn
up? I got this fraught
relationship with these
creative ideas in my head, and so
I was thinking about my own
weird relationship with creativity
and I realized
the best metaphor for me is that
creativity is a chronic
illness. Which I know
sounds horrifying
But here me out. Because what
happens is I go two weeks
three weeks, four weeks, and
eventually something makes
me angry, something wells
up inside of me
and then I have an
episode of creativity
and I emit a blog post or
a library or a
framework. And
the way I think of it is
it's like kidney stones
I'm passing npm modules
And then I feel a sense of relief
after. So I've seen this pattern
in my life, right? I've got all of
these negative emotions, this
toxicity. I'm a really sad,
broken individual and
over the course of my professional
life I keep finding these
ways to shape that
into positive outcomes
and I don't know how that happens,
and so this talk is an exploration
into trying to figure that out, and maybe
there's something that you can
relate to. Because what I've found
is that that reframing
of what creativity is
certainly lowers the
bar, it's like "are you a broken
individual? Good! then you
can be creative, too!" So let's
wind all the way back to
the beginning of my career
I was working at a big
accounting firm, I wasn't very
competent. I didn't have
very much autonomy
at my job, and I would get
ideas like anyone gets ideas
But I wouldn't be able to act on
those ideas, so they actually just
bummed me out. In fact, eventually
the ideas would fade away
and that would make me feel relieved,
because now they weren't stressing me
out. And it took me years to realize
that what I was missing was
I didn't have an outlet to practice
those creative ideas
To develop a feedback loop, just
like we do with coding stuff
And I learned once I started
trying that production
wasn't necessarily the
best creative outlet, either
Us as developers working at machines
At work, we might think that
this is creativity, building
ideas, but typically they're
other people's ideas
we're building reports, or
mailers, or shopping carts
and we feel creative, because
we did create it
but because it wasn't our own, it doesn't
really scratch the same itch, I don't think
Separately, we usually
work on teams and an important
part of building software on teams
(there's me and that's my team)
An important part about building software
on teams is that we're building everything
to be very consistent and orderly so
that any of us can be productive
in that environment, but creativity is sporadic
and messy. I might have an
idea like "Hey I could pull this
one package out and that would eliminate
the need for these two packages
Because I could put a factory in front
of them and look at this, and this is
really cool and I could be really proud
of the creative thing that I just did
But from everyone else's
perspective, they see the
system is becoming less stable
and less workable. And
they're worried, and I get mad because
they don't appreciate this cool
creative thing that I just
did and then they
get angry because I keep going off
the reservation and disrupting the
orderliness of the system. A third thing that
we see happen a lot at our company
Test Double is, developers
who are passionate about what
they do, they put a lot of effort
they tie up their ego in the stuff that
\they build and then they hand it off
they get excited and then it
just sits in QA
or people comment on their
pull requests and
and things take forever
and they don't see
it in front of users and then
eventually they just get angry
because what they did was
they ceded control
of their happiness and their
emotional state to somebody else
and at work that's just not appropriate,
because we're not building
this stuff for our own good
we need another place to practice
creativity. So you have to create
your own space where that's
safe. And one morning, I was
taking a shower. Ideas come to me in the
shower, I don't know when they come to you
but they always come to me in
the shower, and I had an idea and
it made me angry, of course, because
ideas are bad like I explained earlier
and I got so mad
at this idea that
I went and sat at my computer and
I hacked at it until I could build a thing
I felt that relief again,
but this relief was
different. This was like
the first green bar
in the test. This was like "OK,
cool, I understand this now"
And I went from a
disgruntled employee
to a merely gruntled employee
because I was starting to learn
how to be productive
with creativity
And from then on when
I got a creative idea
in the shower, I'd roll my eyes
because now I've gotta make time
for this—maybe there goes my
Saturday or my evening or something
But at least I had a reasoned
way to work through it
And so ever since I
started programming
professionally, I've always had a main
project that occupies most of my time
and most of my focus, but a little
project to the side. Whenever I get
frustrated or I want to play with
something or I'm learning something
I can pull on that thread as well,
and I always balance both
of these things. Of course
this comes with risks
I'm very often burning
the candle at both ends
If I work all weekend because I'm
so excited about my side project
then I come to work on Monday morning,
the last thing I want to do is program
That can be problematic, and
in the last several years
in particular I've spent so
much time on the road, doing all
this open source stuff on top of
my normal job, that I'm
often asking "Why do I do
this?" And that's where
the introspection
of this talk is—part of
why I did this
talk is that I don't think that I'm that
special. I think all of us could be this
creative and it would save me a
lot of time if you all would
do the talks instead of me
So when I sat and I
thought about why is it
that I do this
I'm almost ashamed to
admit those sources
because they're from my childhood, so
I've got a few little childhood anecdotes
The first one's about golf. My
dad was actually an amateur
golfer. One of my first
memories is watching my
dad play golf on TV at
an amateur PGA event
and so in southeastern Michigan,
every well-to-do businessperson
wanted my dad in their foursome,
so I spent as a kid
a ton of time at country clubs with
kids that were way richer and
more world-weary and experienced
and knowledgeable
and well-to-do than me
that was an important part of my
upbringing, because it taught me the
ever-important skill of
feeling inadequate
Talk about my church a little bit
I went to a church that didn't
necessarily work in its community
and serve the poor or anything
like that. I went to an upper
crust white evangelical
Presbyterian church where I
spent years 5
through 10 of my life learning
how to understand very
intangible concepts and
then feel extremely
strongly about them and argue
with passionate rhetoric
and that was also a really important
skill, because I learned
righteous indignation. Fun fact,
about me: nobody's ever asked
for my opinion, because
no one's ever needed to
I can't help but form
really strong opinions
the minute I see something,
and that's less fun than
it sounds. Third thing
about my life
I'm one of those people, like at
lunch we were talking about college
programs. I got a computer
science degree
in college, and I wasn't
very good at it
My professors pulled me aside senior
year when I was trying to find a job
and some of them confided in me
that maybe I should find a more
hybrid role where I'm also talking
to people more and maybe
not trusted with a computer
and it was through there
that I learned this
real deep-grained incompetence and
what's funny about all those three things is
that clearly they're negative but they have
flip sides that I think are
really valuable to exploit
The inadequacy leads to me
having a bunch of
people that I aspire to in
my life—that I look up to
The indignation means that
I always have something to say
or a perspective (whether
it's valid or not) and
the incompetence means I don't
view myself as a rockstar, I always
feel like I've got a lot to
learn and a lot to improve
That translates to a means, a
motive, and an opportunity
to exploit creative ideas
Also, worth mentioning here is this
these are all markers of tremendous
amounts of privilege in my upbringing
most kids don't have the amount
of spare time that I did to
nurse my existential grief
to the extent that I have,
but through doing
a lot of creative stuff, I've learned
how awesome and how enriching
and rewarding it can be. And
getting back to Todd & I
forming Test Double, a big reason we did
that is because we want everyone to be
able to have that experience by
moving at a sustainable pace
by being able to build creative
stuff in a way that's congruent
with our normal work life, so
that you don't have to be
working on nights &
weekends or particularly
privileged to be able to enjoy
the fruits of creativity
If you want to talk
to us about that
you can e-mail join@testdouble.com.
Our first
step in our recruiting process is really
low-pressure, it's not some sort of
technical interview at a white board,
it's literally a conversation about
how we work and how you work
and whether you'd like to try how
we work. Just to learn about us
and learn a little bit about
what we've learned about productive,
autonomous software development
So anyway, all these
things: really negative
How does that lead to
creative ideas? Well, I
kind of feel like it's a game of MadLibs™
in my head. This is my user
story for creativity. I feel
righteous indignation, but I
don't know what I'm doing
Maybe, if I build
something I will feel
less inadequate.
And I have 9
little anecdotes. 9 little stories of
side projects over my career
that have helped me to mitigate
some of that toxicity
in my heart. And I'm going to
start by talking about
incompetence. Because like I mentioned,
I wasn't very good in college and
I was really worried: why would anyone
ever pay me to write software?
when I can barely learn how
to do it? And my library
at the time where I worked said "Hey, we need
a new citation editor"
on the web. And I
thought, you know, I'm
up to this challenge. I feel
like I don't need this
Computer Science hifalutin stuff,
but I also don't know how to
build apps, either, so maybe
if I build it I'll at least
find a way to survive this profession,
and it was a pretty low
pressure gig, because it
was $10 an hour and I could
spend all summer on it. So I built
this thing called
KnightCite, a little citation
editor on the web. It was free
and I was really proud, I did
it. I accomplished a lot
of my goals. It supports all
the major styleguides, dozens
of sources (the only one that
did that). Has an account
system where you can login, create
bibliographies, and export them
It's got millions of users,
and still to this day it's by
far the most-used piece of software
that I've ever written, and
I made it all up as I went. I didn't
read in a book how to do this
I just had to figure out how
to do a reset password
thing, and I just figured it
all out as I went. This, of course
had some very minor downsides.
Like, for instance, it's totally
insecure.
It's 100% manual testing
It produces gigabytes of
daily server warnings
That those poor admins who still
are, over a decade
later, still dealing with
and it's one 16,000
line-long PHP file
of just if's and else's
and string concatenation
But
what had happened to me in my
classroom education was it had
drilled into me this fear that
I don't get what's going on
and paralyzed me from ever
practicing any of that creative
reflex and that creative
muscle. So recognizing
that I needed a safe space where
it was OK to make a mess
and to do that in concert
with learning proper
computer science-y
stuff was crucial
to me even being
in this profession
much less on a stage, talking
to you all about it. So that
certainly lessened my sense
of incompetence. The
other thing at the time, the web
was just a really fancy hypercard
implementation. I didn't feel like a
real developer; my friends all worked
on airplane realtime controls and operating systems
so the web versus being
closer to the metal. Like, Uncle
Bob told me—is Uncle Bob still
here today, that you're
not a real programmer
unless you programmed assembly—well,
I hadn't really programmed a lot of assembly
So I didn't feel like a real
programmer. And so I
tried to go native at multiple
points in my career
Maybe on a Saturday, I'd open up Xcode
and say, "I'm gonna build an OS X
app", and i'd look at the documentation
and it would confuse me and I'd feel
stupid, and then I'd wait a weekend
and I'd go, and I'd
find a different part of the documentation
and it'd depress me, and I'd feel
stupid. And then the week after that
I would open up Xcode and I'd
look at a different part—and this outside
in, like, "maybe if I just read it all
and then I'll know how to make native
apps." Of course, that didn't go well
and time kept passing and
I just concluded I was
probably too dumb to make
native apps, maybe I just had
stay on the web. But then one
day, a momentous day that a lot
of us remember: the iPhone was
announced. And I thought to myself
as soon as this thing has
an SDK, I'm gonna
make an app. I really want
to build something for
the iPhone. The only problem was I
had no idea what that would be. So I
got the original iPhone
and it changed
my life, right? It was beautiful, obviously.
It's innovative, there's nothing like it.
I knew from the first day
I had it that it was
life-altering, because I took my wife
to a restaurant and I ignored her the
whole time. And I was, like, "this is
the future!" Boy was I right
So, the thing about that was I
was staring so long, because
Edge was so slow
and I had this one gaming forum
I liked to visit, and
at first it was not very
readable, but it took like
3 minutes to load
a single page
of what were often 50,
60 page-long threads
so that was unacceptable. But
there  was no such thing as
the mobile web at the time. There's
certainly no responsive
design, and so I thought to myself, maybe
I could build an app that was like a
client to this website. Because I felt
like the mobile web was a joke
but I kept failing to learn
Cocoa, and so maybe
if I built something, I'd at
least learn how to learn a
really unfamiliar thing and
tackle a new platform
and I did it. So I started by
building a little system that just
go and fetch the HTML, and then
I figured out how to load a library
like libxml2 and parse
all that into an object
model, and then, you know,
I'd find all the media in those
objects and go and fetch them
from the Internet, so I could build a
UI and have a custom user
interface in an iPhone app
and you know what, it was way faster,
and it was legible, and it was
full-featured, you could log in and
edit posts and stuff, it was really neat
it was also the very first time I ever
contributed to open source in a real
way, and it was so
cool, because every time that the
Facebook app got launched, a
little bit of my code ran, and when
I realized the impact that I
could have that way, I got addicted
to sharing my stuff in
open source. It was also my very
first user group talk, and so
the only reason I'm here today is because
this one app happened to go well
of course, it was rejected by Apple
because, sometimes people swear
on the Internet. And swearing
was against the guidelines, which
were very prudish at the time
and so I threw it in the
trash. But I didn't care
I was happy as a clam, because mission
accomplished: I'd learned how to learn a thing
That was the real purpose
for that exercise, and
what I learned there was that learning
something simple is pretty easy so
long as you can fit it inside a
day or whatever the bounds
of that passion is, because
it's enough to get
through a weekend, but when
the going gets tough, your motivation
fizzles. If you try to learn something
bigger, that's going to take several
days, weeks, months, then
you really need a purpose
that's going to push you through
those barriers as time
goes on, or else you'll get
distracted, you'll end up with just
a graveyard of half-finished
projects everywhere
So what I try to do is find the
smallest thing I can possibly
caremad about. Really, like, "I need
this project to exist
and I'm going to just push and
drag it over the finish line"
And that was a lot of valuable
lessons, and certainly
made me feel less incompetent as a
developer, because I got to go native
For a long time, I did Java development
and Java's a cool language,
but I felt like it was
a little uncool. It was
certainly not getting a lot of
buzz in the mid-aughts
certainly not like Ruby was. A
lot of my friends, they
seemed really cool, they all
worked on Ruby at work
and the best way I can compare
the two languages is via
Super Mario Kart. You might
think of Java
as being like one of the early
courses, just like a really
wide lane and you can't
really mess up that badly
If you go off the course,
you can just drive back
on and we get that with
Java, because it's not a
very expressive language. The
compiler does a lot for you
the tools do a lot for you. Ruby
is more like Rainbow Road
where it's narrower and faster
and if you fall off, Lakitu
has to pick you up
and you lose like 20 seconds,
and that's reflective of
dynamic programming and
metaprogramming and how
you don't have the same amazing
tooling. And so programming
even at this point in my career, I felt
like I wasn't a very good programmer
much less dynamic programming.
And at the time
in Ruby, meta-programming—
changing at runtime the
object model, the classes
and method definitions
I didn't even understand how that
could possibly work. So I joined
my first Ruby team completely terrified
and surrounded by people who
were way cooler than me and I
thought "I have nothing to contribute
here" until I looked at
their test suite
Because in Java, we had a
pretty formal sense of what
good tests looked like, and I knew
that Rubyists wrote a lot of tests
But it turns out that they all
sucked, and so when I looked
at those tests, I thought maybe this
is a way for me to sneak in
the back door and actually be
relevant. I looked at a test like this
This is creating a fake dog
object and it's saying
the dog should be called with the
method wag and the argument tail
and then you pass the dog
to your subject under test
and this just looked way wrong to me.
First, there's no type awareness
so you don't know that dog
actually responds to wag. Then
these things are out of order. It's like
given-then-when and that feels
awkward. And the API for making that
test double and stubbing it
was kinda confiusing, so
I got caremad enough to say maybe
I hate these mock objects, but if I
can't metaprogram Ruby, I can't
build something to replace them
so maybe if I build it, I'll at
least find a way to fit in
as a Rubyist. And my whole
goal here was just to
cargo-cult my favorite test double
library in Java and implement it
in Ruby. And it turns out that
that didn't work so well
I learnedl some
humility in the process that I had to
go and actually talk to humans about
the idioms and conventions in Ruby.
I had to really bone up and learn
how the Ruby object model worked.
And then I had to put the time
in. I took two weeks off for Christmas
that year and I spent the whole time
squirreled away just working
on this, which my family
didn't appreciate. And so what came
out is this little fun gem called
gimme. You pass it a type
it's got the type awareness built-in.
Here I pass it [to] the subject
It's in the correct order. Here you
can say you verify that the
dog's called with wag and tail in a
way that looks like a method
invocation. And so I was really proud because
this had the type awareness I was looking
for. It preserves the test order.
Has a clever, terse Ruby
like API. Of course, no one
adopted it, because nobody
knew who I was, but I shopped it around
at a couple conferences and got people
like Jim Weirich to incorporate
this style into Flexmock
and now RSpec—which
was the first example—
has incorporated the same style.
So I was able to kind-of move
the needle a little bit. But
what that project taught me
was it's important to get
out of the line of fire, right?
I don't want to try to
learn how to metaprogram in the
most important feature, because
then I'm on the spot, and everyone's
going to call me out as an imposter
Meanwhile, I learned
that working code
can sell an idea way better
than just nitpicking stuff
if I just come to that team and say  "hey
your tests suck, because I don't like this
and this and this", they'd say "what,
so?". But if you throw a keyboard at
the problem and actually build something—a
proof of concept—you can reframe the
discussion around the concrete stuff,
and that was how I was able to sell
that idea. Additionally, if what
you're selling is ideas
the best part is they require no maintenance.
Nobody is going to open up a GitHub
issue at 3am on a Saturday
because your idea stopped
working and so it's true that thoughtleaders
have more fun. So that made me certainly
feel less incompetent. A little bit
about my own sense of inadequacy
and how I was able to deal with that
I practice a thing called
Midwestern programming
So if this is the continental
US, my general
stereotyped perception is that people
on the east coast, the developers
there they have serious jobs.
They work at universities doing
high finance, it's very
obviously valuable
work because it creates a lot of money.
And on the west coast, your apps
obviously don't make any money,
but they get a lot of attention and
all the really, really
popular snacklechat, and other
stuff, everyone is sort of…
but in the midwest,
we do a lot of charts
We have all these blue
chip companies that have backend
office apps that they need
built that might only have
three users, that might
not be that exciting. So
frankly, I'm just not
great at cocktail parties, when I
explain, "Oh, well we're building
this system that participates
in demand-response energy
markets in various parts of the
country", people… their eyes glaze
over and I heard a certain amount of
rockstar envy. I just wanted to build a cool
thing that I could say in a sentence,
people would know what I did
so I felt like my work wasn't exciting,
but I only really knew how to build
enterprise stuff, so maybe if I built
something that was just designed to
go viral, I'd feel
more appreciated
There was a service called mustachify.me
at the time. My friend Aidan
wrote, and what you do is pass
an image and then it would
use face.com API and put
mustaches on the faces
and I thought "that was cool, but
let's go bigger". Like, what could I
build that leveraged this, so I made
a Chrome extension called Must
Stache. And my friend
Cory and I wrote it
and so basically we would just
go to the mustachify service, replace
all the images on every page in
your browser with a mustachified one
and we though this was really
cool, we did it in like 3 hours
posted to a forum at night, we went to
bed. And then the next day we had like
3000 installs of Pro users
so they were visiting 40
pages an hour, or 42
images per tab and
we did the back-of-the-napkin math to realize
it was like 5 million requests per hour
and we learned a valuable lesson
on that first day. It's actually a
popular meme right now called
serverless architecture, because
we just destroyed
Aidan's poor dyno. So we had to
go back to the drawing board
and what we did was we rebuilt it
but this time talking directly to the
face.com API which did the facial
recognition and got you JSON
back. And then with that JSON
we'd take our own image and
then just rotate, transpose, and
put it over the images ourselves
And that was really fun. That
was a fun weekend hack
But I didn't get a ton of attention.
In fact time passed
I forgot all about this thing until I
saw in the news that face.com
was getting acquired for
$80 Million by facebook
that made me—that was
surprising. So I went googling
around my Must Stache thing and saw
it had been covered in Tested
it'd been covered in PC
World in print. It
was on the Verge. You know, the
Glamour magazine wrote an article
about this Chrome extension. And no
one ever thought to contact me
But I felt pretty
proud that I'd had this
impact. And pretty
annoyed too when I thought
about it. I looked at face.com's
developer forums and almost all the
posts were just people using my
stupid Must Stache thing, and
the developers at face.com were
giving them active tech support.
And I thought "but this is violating
your terms of—ohhhhh, it's so
that you hockey stick and can
show off a ton of usage to
Facebook, and I bet you a big
part of that $80M valuation
had something to do with
my thing. Where's my
cut? Well, my cut
came in the form of face.com shutting
down and then me getting a bunch of
e-mail because all of a sudden,
nobody's browser worked
Because all of the images
would just 404
So that was cool. I
built a popular
thing, yay, but I didn't get to
enjoy any of that popularity
at all, and I may have
made somebody else
millions of dollars [citation
needed]. But it feels
that way and I made
lots of users angry
the only time they ever learned about
me was after their stuff stopped
working. And I was left
with no recourse
I didn't have time to build a new
face.com, I just had to kind of
shut down the extension.
So I learned in the process
serverless isn't. Obviously, if you
depend on someone else's server
they can always pull
the rug out from you
That was a valuable
lesson. Also, chasing
popularity without an underlying
purpose or value statement is
toxic. Because, when I did
run into a problem, I didn't have
the time—there was no economic
reason or even moral reason
for me to invest the time to fix
it. I was just left, you know,
with people angry at me.
So that sucked.
But! It did get covered, apparently,
in the last season of
HBO's Silicon Valley where
they made an AR
version of the plugin, so
that made me feel
pretty cool, I guess.
Another way that I felt inadequate as
a developer is that one time I was on this
legacy rescue project. A big waterfall
project. If you don't know these
terms, by the way, legacy when
we use that in software terms
it means that your
kids will inherit it
and rescue means that
you want to be rescued
So I was on this
project for months
I could barely—my computer
was just a memory
at this point, because I hadn't programmed
in so long, I'd forgotten how to program
I felt like, "could I even program
anything in 2 months anymore?"
I was really feeling kind of despondent
and out of touch with myself as a
craftsperson. And at the time the
to-do apps were undergoing this
renaissance, because it was still
early in the App Store and there was all these
new to-do apps and I didn't really like any
of them. I kept falling back on this
plaintext thing that I did where
I'd define a project with a colon,
and I'd dasherize tasks
and I'd indicate something's
done with a slash or blocked
with a pound sign, or I'd
date it with braces and I
would just do this instead of using an
app, but of course that was inconvenient
So I was thinking at the time,
I feel like I hate all these
to-do apps, but I've also
forgotten how to code so I can't
built my own. But maybe if I were to
try I'd at least be able to restore my
dignity as a developer. And what I had
to do there was I could give myself
the constraints needed and
so I gave myself a little quest
I said "I want to build a
to-do app that's so great
that I will use this at the
exclusion of all the others…
and I only want to give
myself 24 hours."
Can I still hack it?
Under pressure.
So I built this app called doing-it.
So in doing-it, you define a project.
And I started by just saying
throw all the content in a div,
[make it] contenteditable
dump it into localStorage,
read it from localStorage
and then use the tool to track
the rest of the work in the tool
So I was using doing-it to
build doing-it from like minute
40. So I did it, I built the
thing. It's still up at
todo.testdouble.com if you
want to check it out you can
make a project, it'll autoformat
based on the
the lead character here, so this is
me making a couple different things
I can mark them done or
overdue or high priority
and mark'em all done. And that was a lot
of fun, you know I finished it within the
1 day. Gave me a renewed sense
of confidence as a developer
It still works, thanks to
Heroku's free dynos
No users, so no angry e-mails to
deal with. That was nice. And
I just threw it up on GitHub
Because that's just the default
thing, I just work in the open
But the purpose of course was
just self-validataion that's what
I wanted to prove myself I could
still program, but when I throw
stuff out into the open, that's just because
that's my default, it's not because
I'm necessarily trying to become
an open source star. But I do
get a lot of people—because I do a lot
of open source—come to me and say
"How do I get into open source", and I
think that maintainers struggle with this
question, because they want to
make it sound easy to get involved
They might say, "write me
some docs" or "Send me a
small pull request or something", and
the problem with that of course is that
it's not the normal creative
exchange of ideas. You might
even submit the pull request, but
then most of the time that maintainer
is gonna get angry and say "this
isn't how I'd do it—rejected!"
or "Change it!" and nobody
needs another boss
right? So if you get
into open source
to be creative, you just
create stuff instead
Because, when you go and talk to open source
maintainers, like "how did you get started
with open source," it was rarely "oh,
I started doing docs for this
one other guy. It was usually
"well, I made stuff that I
wanted, I threw it up on the Internet,
and then some of it got popular
and most of it didn't." And
you'll never predict what's
gonna stick and what's not. The reference
to 200 repos is that I've probably
got like 250 repos that
I've started and you've—
—odds are you've heard of zero of
them. You may have heard of two or
three. But the vast majority
is stuff that I just built
just for the sake of it, and I don't
expect to hear about it again
And it might seem scary to
work in the open, like
you know, people are going to criticize
your code, but there's a secret:
nobody reads code. So
just don't worry about that.
I'm not going to read your code
So that made me feel a little
bit less inadequate
as a developer. Third one, now
that I'm a self-professed
thoughtleader who talks at
conferences a bunch, most
thoughtleaders get into this
line of work, by doing something
interesting, or observing something
interesting. Sharing that insight with
other people. But then
eventually, you stop doing
the work, and you run the risk of
thoughtleading other people straight off
a cliff. And you don't
want to do that
When it comes to test-driven development,
I talk about test-driven development
a lot. I've talked about it for more
years than I've practiced
it, which is worrying. And one day
I decided to start leading
some thoughts about test-driven
development. In fact, if you google
the phrase tdd failure, this
blog post is the top
result, which I"m particularly proud of
And I got a lot of attention. And it was
the front-page of Hacker News and I was
in the article I was saying "well this is what
London-school test-driven development
is", and then the guy who actually
invented that, Nat Pryce, was like
"no, it's not, really", and I
was like "But I just got 400
thousand page views saying it was" and
now everyone's going to find out that I'm a big
idiot. And so I was really
upset about that, but
then, being the opportunistic and
person just seeking the
validation of everyone else, I
decided to pivot and instead
just rename what I do
as its own thing, so I
call it "Discovery Testing"
and I actually built libraries
and talks around how to practice
Discovery Testing as its own school
of TDD. So much so, that I
realized I give a lot of talks
but I hadn't actually
practiced it much
and I was just full of hot air. And
so I felt like TDD, of course
it's not very well understood.
A lot of us try it and fail
or don't really learn how to apply
it consistently, so there's stuff
to say here, but I've just become
a talking head at this point
And so I realized this last
summer, maybe I need to
start practicing this more on my
own and really proving out
that it really works. I've gotta validate
my ideas. So I've got this
Simplisafe alarm system. It's
just a thing where you
stick it to the wall, and if a door
opens, an alarm goes off, police come to
your house. Simple alarm monitoring
And I love Apple's HomeKit,
because I really love this idea
of a smart home, like we learned
today the Internet of Things
aside from denial of service attacks
is also useful for just the convenience
of controlling your domain.
So I have this server called
homebridge, runs Node.js and
you can build adapters, so I was thinking
I'll build an adapter for Simplisafe
So that when I'm on my couch I
can say "hey Siri, turn on my alarm"
The idea being, of course, I'd
spend 40 hours building
a thing to save myself 8 seconds
the 3 or 4 times that I think
to use the thing, because programming.
So the question was: what's this
thing in the middle? How do I
build an adapter? The truth is I had no
idea how to build this, and that's
purportedly what my practice of test-
driven development, Discovery Testing
does. So does my process
actually work? And so I actually
experimented, and several
hours in I was very
relieved to find that I could build
a thing and that it actually worked
So there's this npm module now
exists, simplisafe and it's got
a simple little API. You pass it
credentials, you get a
client back, you can set the state.
What was funny was I TDD'd
this, right, so I was writing tests. And the
only credentials I had were the ones
to my house. And so I had to be really
careful in the failure states, because I
didn't want to send the cops
to my house by accident
And in particular, this got really
confusing with Travis [CI], because I
would upload it to Travis
continuous integration, and people
would send pull requests and it would
change the beeping in my house and I'd
have to make sure all the doors were shut
But the lesson I learned
there, I followed
my own advice and really practice
it. I was relieved to see that it
went well. But honestly, I'm kind of ashamed
because I went so long without validating
my ideas. And you guys,
just by having
me here today, have given me
a platform and I don't want to
abuse it by just being a talking head.
I want to make sure that everything I
share can potentially really
help you grow in your career
So that was a valuable
lesson and I think
we can apply it to
managers, like technical
managers, former
developers, what I've
been able to generalize from my experience,
especially at Test Double, is that everything
at a distance seems
simpler. The people
actually doing the work, when a developer says this
is going to take several more weeks, they're
closer to it, they see all the
complexity, which is easy
to just hand-wave away when
you're operating at a distance
Additionally, when you have a
lot of experience, you tend to
—we're all pattern-recognition machines and you
feed in all these problems and somebody might
feed you a problem, and you might say
"well, yeah, that looks like the 15 other
things that I did." And you come
up with this round, polished idealistic
solution. But, of course, that's not
going to actually map very closely
to that individual's context. You
have to actually trust the people
closest to the work.
And so that's been a humbling
exercise in a manager role, to not
just jump to conclusions
that I always know best.
But nonetheless, that was
also helpful in me dealing
with my own sense of inadequacy
as I merge into this
more management role. Let's
talk a little bit about indignation
First of all, I'm a big worrier
Todd, mentioned I'm really
high anxiety. I worry about
banks, and credit card statements,
and finances, and stuff
and I really wanted a dashboard
to handle this all for me and Mint
was that for a long time. I'd use
Mint, I'd see all my finances
were still there, and
I'd feel good. But
six years in, I had this random thought:
you know I wonder how Mint
is actually secure? How does it actually
securely go and get all these
services? And get all
my account updates?
Of course, what I figured out
was that it's just not secure
it has decryptable versions
of all of your passwords
to all of your banking stuff and doesn't
support two-factor auth or anything like
that. And that's kind of worrisome.
It's actually a very popular Internet
cloud architecture right now called SPoFaaS.
If you're not familiar with SPoFaaS, it stands
for single point of failure as a service
Another thing we're learning about
today, too, with the Internet outage
So, Mint, Yodlee, if they go away
then all of your stuff just
disappears. You're just giving
a single point of failure for them to take
all your money. So I was stewing on this
I got angry. I was trying to figure
out how do I get off Mint.
Sure, I could cancel it, but I want to replace it
with something better. What could I build
So I thought: security matters.
But I'm not an expert. I'm not going
to build the next Mint or Yodlee
and solve this very difficult distribution
problem, but I could probably
just build something for myself
and at least personally feel a
little bit safer. And so I built this
gem that I call fine_ants
In fine_ants you build adapters. So
here's an adapter to Vanguard
I pass it credentials. And because
I can run it locally, I can
actually do two-factor auth in my terminal,
so I have two-factor auth set up
now. And it just downloads all my
holdings for all my Vanguard accounts
And I built a little Rails
app for it too that
runs at localhost, and so it's
encrypted on my disk
And it shows me all of my account
holdings and I click that button and it
launches a Selenium
worker to go and
open browsers to go to all
of my banks and stuff
And I was really proud, because now
I've almost got this dashboard that I wanted
It's locally-encrypted. It's as safe
as running it from my own browser
Puts Selenium for good use
to once, instead of just
really brittle integration
tests, and
and, you know, admitting it's
not a generalizable app. I mean, you
can go and find this stuff on
GitHub and clone it yourself and run it yourself,
and I'd encourage you to try it
But it's not going to be
the next unicorn, billion
dollar company. But, honestly,
there's no shame in hobby
grade. A lot of times, we're talking about
creativity, right? We're talking about
building stuff. And sometimes
just solving your own
problem is enough. Like these little
toy apps like this are often
what got us into programming in
the first place, even if you're just
solving your own problem,
there's no shame in that. So that
made me feel a little
bit less furious
at the world. Another example, so
Test Double, our company, right.
I've already referred—I used
the term "test double" a few times, but some
of you may not know it. That library
gimme is actually an example of
a test double library. If you don't
know the term, the word "test double" is
supposed to evoke the image of a
stunt double. But not like a
stunt driver in a plane, like
a stand-in for your tests. So
assume you like, maybe
your app depends on the cloud, so you have
to fake that out to make your
test pass. Well, whatever you did
to fake out the cloud is probably
an example of a test double that
fakes that service out
And in JavaScript, the most
popular test double
library is called Sinon. But when
I see people use Sinon, most of them
don't understand it very well
Because it's kind of confusing. A
lot of people get frustrated
because it's a huge API,
or just angry at the
fact it's not very opinionated.
So I've given
a lot of thought to making something
better than Sinon in JavaScript
And I decided, you know, a lot of users
that use Sinon are in pain,
but I have to admit I
can't beat it. It's got like 2
million downloads a month
But if I build something at least
I'll be less grouchy and at least I'll
have something to hand somebody
instead of just more snark
and whining. And so it was
humbling, right, because
I've built now—this is like
the 4th or 5th test double
library in a different language that I've built
and I keep coming back to the same
saw over and over again.
And it's humbling to think
that my entire career
may well hinge on just
two or three concepts and
I keep repeating them, because
I learn, because I'm passionate
about it, and then I build
something and then I share it, and
then I feed back into learning more
and it's this infinite loop of me
iterating over time on just a handful
of issues, and with Test
Double, we're able to
do that again by building testdouble.js.
You can install it on
npm. To get the npm install, and
the npm package "testdouble" it works
on the frontend and the backend
There's a screencast on our
website called happier tdd with
testdouble.js you can go watch.
We've also got a comparison
blog post of testdouble vs. sinon and
what was cool about testdouble
is it works, but it
most importantly, shares all of our
opinions about what we've learned
about test double libraries and
good isolation testing over the years
And it's certainly better than
just being cynical and snarky
about "oh, JavaScript sucks" or
"JavaScript testing is this or that"
A lesson I learned
early on is that if
your message isn't getting through
to somebody and they're not hearing
what you're trying to say, you
can conclude one of two things:
you can either conclude that they're
a bozo for not understanding
you, or that there's something with
how you're trying to communicate that's
failing to convey to them. And if
you conclude that they're a bozo
that's it. You just
disengage, right? There's
no next step. But
I always assume it's something
wrong in how I'm
trying to communicate, and so
I'm always iterating on my message
and only as a very last
possibility do I assume it's
the listener's fault, because
I can't control that at all
And also, for your library
to win, not everything else has to lose.
Sometimes just doing something that's
useful for a small group is plenty. Especially
if you're able to communicate
ideas in a way that moves
other people forward
in how they think about something.
And certainly criticism
is easier than contribution.
It's really easy
to be snarky on Twitter and
say something sucks, but
Christian Johansson who
made Sinon, he put himself
out there and it has served
a lot of people really well
and he's a really
really nice guy, but I
spent like two years just shitting
on his work on twitter before
I thought "maybe I should just build
something that serves my needs
instead." So building
that certainly made me a little
less angry about JavaScript testing.
Another thing you may have
noticed is that I like emoji
I've used a few of them
in the slides
And creativity, open source
stuff, can sometimes feel
a little too self-serious and
open source feels "you create,
we depend." Other people
start to pull your stuff
and then all of a sudden
they're really demanding
and it usually starts with: you have
an idea, you want to build a thing
and it's a labor of love and it
brings you joy, but then
eventually companies start
depending on it, and criticizing
or opening issues or acting entitled
and trying to get stuff out
of you for free and that's a big
bummer. In fact I know a lot of open
source maintainers and
what's super consistent
is that they tend to hate
their creations in
proportion to how popular
they are, and that just
seems totally backwards. So I was feeling
kind of exploited and exhausted
at this particular point
in my career. But I can't just escape open
source, I'm not going to
ragequit GitHub and delete all my
stuff and yank all my stuff
and take my ball and go home. So maybe
if I just build something
new, something fresh, I'll find a fresh
start. And the way I did it was, I
decided I was going to build something
that no business could ever want
To just be creative
for the sake of creativity. And sometimes,
even still, if I build something
that I worry that a business
might exploit, might
build a business around and cut
me out, I'll just license it
GPL as if troll them, because then
that way they have to come
to me to obtain a commercial license
This is such a project. I think it is
GPL'd, called emoruby. So there's
not a lot of transpilers
for the Ruby language, but this
one transpiles emoji
into Ruby code. So here's
an example file
listing of emoruby. This is a
class called Heart,
defining a method called wave, printing
out a statement saying hello
and ending those two things. And then
Instantiating the heart and calling wave
So this, if you're not
familiar with emoruby, this
translates to this ruby here,
and it totally works
And it was a lot of fun. So
tl;dr what I learned
on emoruby is that
it's super dumb, it's
just there for fun, it's just there
to be joyful. I actually got a lot of
contributors on it, because they
found fun in trying to map
different keywords and control-
flow structures to what
emoji should that be. But it
brought me a lot of joy
and it's had zero issues
opened against it this year
So it's one of my favorite projects.
It's okay to just build stuff for
yourself. I know some of you are developers here
and you're here with your managers,
hoping they're not looking over your shoulder
right now: it's actually OK just
to build things for fun. The joy
of programming is like
really undervalued and we get
too self-serious about our craft
So that helped lessen
my sense of indignation. Looking
back on all this stuff
is—I wouldn't recognize myself
ten years ago, I think,
because all of this
these creative exercises have really
changed me as a person and I've actually
found a way to mature
and grow up, and
I see you there, I'm saying "hey look creative
stuff, this is easy" but I've
also just lambasted you with
12 years of side projects
and "look at me! look at me! This is a
cool thing I built!" I understand
that might make the bar feel
higher, and you know what
maybe you're right, because it's true that
creativity is not for everyone. Here's a
quick litmus test if you're perfectly
content. And you're totally
fulfilled. And you're OK with
the status quo, then why would you want
to change things? You're right, maybe
you aren't a creative type. You should
just enjoy the beach that you guys have
not too far from here. But
if you have any negative
feelings at all, our culture right
now, we tend to pathologize
negative feelings as themselves
being bad, but often they're just a
symptom of some different root
cause, and if you analyze and
you're open about that with
yourself, you might find that what's
really bothering you is that you're
using the wrong tool for the job, or
there's friction between the technologies
and the practices that you're using
or work can't offer you what you need,
or maybe you just have your own internal
baggage that you need to get over. And
creativity can be a great outlet
for those kind of root cause
problems. And if you reflect
on how you feel and you
feed—you accept—
those emotions, what's funny
is our asynchronous brain will just
start spitting out ideas and
it'll be a big idea generator
and hopefully, you'll find
a way to exercise it.
And when I tell you, like when you
feel confused, or when you feel down, or
upset or scared, all
of those emotions are the
place where all the good stuff
comes from. Great ideas don't
come from people who've
already got everything
figured out, and
when the bar's that low, you
fling over it and hopefully
wind up in a better place. The important
thing is you've gotta find your outlet
And I don't know what that
outlet is for everybody
In fact it's important for me to mention
that that outlet might not have anything
to do with software. Certainly, if
my outlet for creativity wasn't software,
my wrists wouldn't hurt as much and I'd probably
get more sun and I'd be in better shape
So find what that outlet
is for you, because it may or may not
have anything to do with software
Tomorrow, I was here last year,
and the day after SCNA
was one of my favorite days
last year, because I just sat
on Manhattan beach and watched
football and drank with Big Ten football
from 9am to 3pm which is
something I can't do in the
eastern time zone, so that was really
cool. But tomorrow tomorrow,
we're going to have even more fun,
because we're going to be here
programming stuff. Todd
my partner and I, we're going to join
forces tomorrow and we're doing
what we call a "test smells",
like "code smells" workshop
it's a really fun, engaging
thing where we all talk
together about things about
testing that we hate
I hope that you come and
join, and what we do is
listen to stories, and we've
got this repository of
30 different types of problematic
tests, work through
those examples and really kind of
bring a name to a lot of the different
antipatterns that we find in tests. I
hope that you'll join us, it's a really
really fun exercise, and it's going
to be happening kind of coincident
with the code retreat and
what other activities we have
tomorrow. So again, my name's @searls
or Justin, you can call
me whatever you like
I hope you tell me on Twitter what you
thought of this talk, any feedback
you have. Like I mentioned,
we're here to
fix the software industry and
to do that we're gonna
need creative people who want to
creatively solve those problems and help
inspire that in others. If you're
interested in joining, our
team I hope you'll contact us.
And if you know any
teams that are looking for
that slack. Looking for some
outside inspiration, we're
always looking for
additional clients that we can work with. You
can reach us at hello@testdouble.com
or find me or Todd tonight or
tomorrow, we'd love to talk to you
Also got a lot of stickers and
business cards we'd like to share
But, you know, you've been
super patient. Like Todd
mentioned, I'm the only one standing
between you and free drinks
and nobody got up
and left, so that's
really humbling. Thank you so
much for your time today.